Guide to the Nina Wilcox Putnam Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nina Wilcox Putnam papers
1929-1962
YCAL MSS 428
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.76
(9 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
The Nina Wilcox Putnam papers contain writings, correspondence, and other materials documenting the life and work of feminist and author Nina Wilcox Putnam. Writings consists chiefly of drafts of short stories and essays dating from the 1930s onward. There are drafts of a few novels, possibly unpublished, and a number of treatments, but the collection does not include material relating to Putnam's longer published works, or her children's book Sunny Bunny (1917), dating from the first two decades of her literary career. Correspondence consists of a small number letters with editors, publishers, and others dating from the early 1950s. The largest file exists for The Reader's Digest, but there are also letters from Gilbert Roland, Frank Scully, and Gloria Swanson. In addition, there are carbons of several outgoing letters dating from 1953 relating to an article by Putnam on Guatemala. Other materials include lists of works by Putnam documenting titles by genre and publisher.
Putnam, Nina Wilcox, 1888-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Nina Wilcox Putnam (1888-1962)
Nina Wilcox Putnam, author, was born in New Haven, Connecticut, the daughter of Marrion Wilcox, a professor of English at Yale, and Eleanor Patricia Sanchez. Putnam was educated at home and published her first piece, a short story, in 1907. She married Robert Faulkner Putnam of the publishing family in 1907; Robert J. Sanderson, a businessman, in 1919; Arthur James Ogle, a Florida real estate agent, in 1931; and Christian Eliot in 1933. Putnam published over twenty books, including novels, children's books, and non-fiction works, and a great many short stories and articles. Summary information is available in the standard biographical resources.
Scope and Contents
The Nina Wilcox Putnam papers contain writings, correspondence, and personal papers documenting the life and work of feminist and author Nina Wilcox Putnam. Writings consist chiefly of drafts of short stories and essays dating from the 1930s onward. There are drafts of a few novels, possibly unpublished, and a number of treatments, but the collection does not include material relating to Putnam's longer published works, or her children's book Sunny Bunny (1917), dating from the first two decades of her literary career. Correspondence consists of a small number letters to and from editors, publishers, and others dating from the early 1950s. The largest file exists for The Reader's Digest, but there are also letters from Gilbert Roland, Frank Scully, and Gloria Swanson. In addition, there are carbons of several outgoing letters dating from 1953 relating to an article by Putnam on Guatemala. Other materials include lists of works by Putnam documenting titles by genre and publisher.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1929-1959. II. Correspondence, 1940-1962. Personal Papers, 1953-1954.
American literature -- 19th century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- Archives; Authors; Putnam, Nina Wilcox, 1888-1962; Roland, Gilbert, 1905-1994; Scully, Frank, 1892-1964; Swanson, Gloria, 1897-1983; Reader's Digest Association
- Writings, 1929-1959; Series I; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title (in quotes) or supplied heading (in brackets).
  Series I, Writings, consists chiefly of drafts of short stories and essays dating from the 1930s onward. There are drafts of a few novels, possibly unpublished, and a number of treatments, but the series does not include material relating to Putnam's longer published works, or her children's book Sunny Bunny (1917), dating from the first two decades of her literary career. Most drafts are typed and many are corrected. In addition to the genre, only the presence of multiple drafts and other physical formats (e.g. "holograph") are noted in folder headings below.
  Many drafts in the series have the name and address of Putnam's literary agents, Jacques Chambrun and others, on the front cover or first page.
  Publication dates have been preserved as bracketed circa dates.
  - "$20,000 a Week," story, undated (Box 1)
  - "Act of God," story, 1932 June 21 (Box 1)
  - "After We Married," essay, undated (Box 1)
  - "An American Schoolmaster in Mexico," essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, [circa 1955] (Box 1)
  - "Answer to an Unmailed Letter," story, drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "Bargain Counter Husbands," drafts, [circa 1945]; 2 (Box 1)
  - "A Beauty Parlour for Saints," essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, [1956?] (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes letter from Putnam, dated 1956, to the editor of The Reader's Digest
  - "Cabin 13," novel, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Champagne," story, holograph, undated (Box 1)
  - "Christmas Gift," story, synopsis, undated (Box 1)
  - "Christophine Discovers America," synopsis, [circa 1935] (Box 1)
  - "The Corpse Talks Back," screenplay, undated (Box 1)
  - "Dance of the Conquerors," treatment, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 1)
  - "Dangerous Woman," story and proposed adaptation, [circa 1944]; 2 (Box 2)
  - "Darwin Was Right," story, undated (Box 2)
  - "Did I Tell You About My Vacation?" holograph, undated (Box 2)
  - "Divorce Is No Solution," essay, [circa 1948] (Box 2)
  - "Don't Knock It," story, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Duck That Laid the Golden Egg," story, drafts, [circa 1936] (Box 2)
  - [The Efficacy of Prayer], synopsis, undated (Box 2)
  - [Ella-Mae], synopsis, undated (Box 2)
  - [Exodus to Mexico?], drafts, holograph and typescript, 1951, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Fighting Parson," synopsis, undated (Box 2)
  - "Flowers for a Lady," story, synopsis and drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - "Fog-Bound," story, synopsis, undated (Box 2)
  - "For Girls Only," essay, [circa 1944 December] (Box 2)
  - "Forbidden Island," novel, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - "Foreign Lands Near Home," essay, undated (Box 2)
  - "Gentlemen for Sale," play, undated (Box 3)
    Includes reader report, dated March 19, 1936, by L.L.
  - "Give Us This Day," script (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
  - "Gladys, Photographer's Model," novel, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Goldfish Are Fine," story, [circa 1935] (Box 3)
  - "Good American," story, [circa 1938] (Box 3)
  - "The Good Cloth of Guatamala," scenario and drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 3)
  - "Have a Pleasant Trip!" proposal for radio or television program, 1949-1950, undated (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence
  - "He Makes the Angels Sing," essay, undated (Box 3)
  - "Headliner," story, undated (Box 3)
  - "Her Excellency the Governor," story, undated (Box 3)
  - "Hi, Neighbor!" drafts, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Hope of Two Heavens," story, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "How Smart Is the Smart Set?" essay, undated (Box 3)
  - "I Am Not Lonely Now," essay, undated (Box 3)
  - [I Had a Cataract Removed?], essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, [circa 1955] (Box 3)
  - "I Went Fishing With Grover Cleveland," story, drafts, holograph and typescript, [circa 1956] (Box 3)
  - "I Wish I Had the Money I've Spent on Liquor," essay, [circa 1942] (Box 3)
  - "If I Had a Million," essay, undated (Box 3)
  - "If I Were Mrs. Mesta," essay, undated (Box 3)
  - "In Your Brown Derby!" story, [circa 1935] (Box 3)
  - "A Lady's Profession," treatment, drafts, 1930; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Laughing Through," story (incomplete), undated (Box 4)
  - "Learn How to Give," essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, [circa 1953] (Box 4)
  - "Lesson from a Tree," essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 4)
  - "Let the Hurricane Blow," story, synopsis and drafts, [circa 1937] (Box 4)
  - "Let Us Spray," essay, drafts, [circa 1947] (Box 4)
  - "Letters from a Self-Made Mother to Her Son," story, drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - "Life Sentence," story, undated (Box 4)
  - "Love Cannot Die," story, 1929 May (Box 4)
  - "Madame Cavalry," story, undated (Box 4)
  - "Make-Believe Marriage," story, undated (Box 4)
  - "Man-Hungry," novel, synopsis, notes, and draft (incomplete), undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - [Mexico City article], essay, undated (Box 4)
    Includes photographs
  - "Miss Daredevil," story, undated (Box 4)
  - "Miss Lieutenant," novel, holograph, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "Money from Home," story, undated (Box 5)
  - "More Precious Than Rubies," synopsis (incomplete), [circa 1951] (Box 5)
  - "The Most Unforgettable Character I've Met: Postman's Holiday," [essay?], drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - "My Friend Stanislaus," story, synopsis, [circa 1951] (Box 5)
  - "My Search For God," essay, synopsis and draft, holograph, [circa 1949] (Box 5)
  - "My Spirit Has a Home Town," essay, synopsis, [circa 1952] (Box 5)
  - "Never Underestimate a Cat," story, undated (Box 5)
  - "New Noah's Ark," poem, undated (Box 5)
  - "Night Work," play, undated (Box 5)
  - "The One-Man Church," story, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - "Out All Night," story, undated (Box 5)
  - "Outline", undated (Box 5)
  - "Painted Doll," story, undated (Box 5)
  - "Pen Points: An Account of an Interlude," essay, undated (Box 5)
  - [Poems], drafts, holograph and typescript, 1955-1959, undated (Box 5)
  - "Pressed Duck," story, synopsis and draft, [circa 1949] (Box 5)
  - "The Price of Applause," story, synopsis, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Puppet-Maker of Puebla," screenplay, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "The Puppet-Maker of Puebla," screenplay, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - "Radio Love Song," novel, undated (Box 6)
  - "Rainbow Chase," story, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - "The Referee Dogs," story, undated (Box 6)
  - "Reply Paid," story, synopsis, [circa 1930] (Box 6)
  - "The Rich Have No Money," novel, synopsis and draft, undated (Box 6)
  - "Romance, Incorporated: The Story of the Palace Hotel," essay, undated (Box 6)
  - "Salt of the Earth," treatment, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "Sawdust Will Tell," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Scandal of the Season," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "Second Chance," story, synopsis and draft, [circa 1939] (Box 7)
  - "Second-hand Book," story, drafts, holograph and typescript, 1957 (Box 7)
    Includes letter, dated October 23, 1957, from The Reader's Digest
  - "Secret Weapon," story, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Serious Business Side of Marriage," essay, undated (Box 7)
  - "Seventh Man," story, synopsis, [circa 1949] (Box 7)
  - "The Seventh Sense," essay, drafts, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Shirt: Drama in Everyday Life," essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, [circa 1953] (Box 7)
  - "Slack Enough," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Snob," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "So You're Going to Build a House!" essay, synopsis, undated (Box 7)
  - "Soft Jobs for Soft Heads," essay, holograph, undated (Box 7)
  - "Some Plain Truths About Santa Claus," essay, undated (Box 7)
  - "Song of Paris," synopsis for musical script, 1931 (Box 7)
  - "Surprise Party," story, synopsis and draft, holograph, undated (Box 7)
  - "Sweet Lightning," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "Taking the Slack from the Seat of Learning," essay, undated (Box 7)
  - "Technical Virgin," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "Teddy Said "Bully For You!"," story, drafts, 1956, undated (Box 7)
    Includes letter from Putnam, dated 7 December, 1956, to The Reader's Digest
  - "The Temple of Venus Dream," story, drafts, undated (Box 7)
  - "Ten Million Teen-Age Girls Can't Be Wrong," essay, undated (Box 7)
  - "That Wonderful Old Car," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "This Was a Greater Glory," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "Those Innocent in Love," novel, undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - "To Catch a Dream," story, drafts, [circa 1954] (Box 8)
  - "Too Fat for Love," essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "Too Many Cooks," essay, holograph, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Umbrella Man," story, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Vanishing Rich," essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "War-Crazy Clothes," essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Warrior Cats," essay, 1946, 1953 (Box 8)
    Includes letter from Putnam, dated 21 May, 1953, to Michele Braidy
  - "Water, Water, Everywhere, Especially in America!" essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "A Wedding in Venice," story, drafts, undated (Box 8)
  - "What Can a Girl of Sixty Do?" essay, [circa 1950] (Box 8)
  - "Wheat," script, 1932 August 27 (Box 8)
  - "Where Do I Go from Home?" essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "Who Put the Limp in Olympics?" essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "Who's to Blame in Guatemala?" essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "Why I Believe in Love," essay, synopsis, [circa 1952] (Box 8)
  - "Why Keep a Secret?" story, undated (Box 8)
  - "Wild Animals Who Have Met Me," essay, drafts, holograph and typescript, 1954, undated (Box 8)
    Includes letter from Putnam, dated January 18, 1954, to Park East Magazine
  - "Women Are Fools to Drink," essay, holograph, undated (Box 8)
  - "Work at Your Dreams," essay, undated (Box 8)
  - "You Haven't Changed a Bit," story, undated (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1932-1962; Series II; 22
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Series II, Correspondence, consists of a small number letters to and from editors, publishers, and others dating from the early 1950s. The largest correspondence file exists for The Reader's Digest, but there are also letters from Gilbert Roland, Frank Scully, and Gloria Swanson. In addition, there are carbons of several outgoing letters dating from 1953 relating to Putnam's article "Who's to Blame in Guatemala".
  - Aldrich, Amey, 1955 April (Box 9)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1953 (Box 9)
  - Cabot, John M. (John Moors), 1953 April (Box 9)
  - Davenport, Wallace, 1960 January 6 (Box 9)
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1953 April 15 (Box 9)
  - Eisenhower, Milton Stover, 1953 April (Box 9)
  - Harper's Magazine, 1953 June 13 (Box 9)
  - Hayes, Helen, 1959, undated (Box 9)
  - Hearst, William Randolph, 1947 March 25 (Box 9)
  - J. P. Morgan & Co., 1955 April 7 (Box 9)
  - Kruif, Paul de, 1950, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Ladies Home Journal, 1958-1959, undated (Box 9)
  - Mexican Life, 1959 May 9 (Box 9)
  - New Haven Register, 1962 (Box 9)
  - Odhams Press, 1953 June 29 (Box 9)
  - The Reader's Digest, 1951-1962, undated (Box 9)
  - Roland, Gilbert, undated (Box 9)
  - Scully, Frank, 1958-1959 (Box 9)
  - Swanson, Gloria, 1958 March 3 (Box 9)
  - Wiley, Hugh, 1956 January 18 (Box 9)
  - Wilkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1940 November 4 (Box 9)
  - Others, 1932-1962, undated (Box 9)
- Personal Papers, 1953-1954; Series III; 4
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Personal Papers, contains lists of works by Putnam and manuscript notes. The lists document Putnam's work by genre and publisher.
  - Lists of works by Nina Wilcox Putnam, 1953-1954, undated (Box 9)
  - Manuscript notes, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Unidentified draft (incomplete?), undated (Box 9)
- Oversize, 1955-1962; 2
  - Writings (In Series I), 1955-1958 (Box 10)
  - New Haven Register clipping (In Series II), 1962 January 19 (Box 11)